Calvin Tomkins Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series II: Major New Yorker Articles, 1961-2006
  - Subseries II.A: Research Files, 1961-2006
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "Running Fence," Christo, 3/28/1977; 1 TLS Mary McChesney-CT (11/8/1976) 1 ALS Lynn Hershman (Associate Project Director)-CT (9/9/1976) [re: unveiling of the project] News clippings, documents, correspondence relating to the project and its opposition, biographical materials and other documents of Mary Fuller McChesney, expenses, official photographs of the project. (Box 17, Folder II.A.66)
    - Profile: "Forms Under Light," Philip Johnson, 5/23/1977; 1 TLS Marga Barr-CT (6/2/1976) [re: her personal recollections of Johnson] 1 ALS Ada Louise Huxtable-CT (n.d.) The Architectural Forum 138:1 (January-February 1973), issue devoted to Johnson, news clippings, offprints and articles, contacts lists, biographical details on MoMA letterhead, research notes and chronology, materials on the Rothko Chapel and from other Johnson churches. (Box 17, Folder II.A.67)
    - Profile: "Forms Under Light," Philip Johnson, 5/23/1977; 1 TLS Robert A.M. Stern-CT (6/22/1976) [re: Johnson's writing] 2 TLS Jane Blaffer Owen-CT (5/19, 6/4/1976) [re: New Harmony Open Church] Four 8x10 photographs of the John F. Kennedy Memorial, Dallas Articles, news clippings, brochures, contacts list, research and bibliographic notes, press packets and brochures on Johnson buildings. (Box 17, Folder II.A.68)
    - Profile: "Forms Under Light," Philip Johnson, 5/23/1977; Tear sheets of Profile, typescript draft with hand edits (7/26/1976). (Box 17, Folder II.A.69)
    - Profile: "Putting Something Over Something Else," Romare Bearden, 11/28/1977; Possible topical index to interview binder 1 ALS Romare Bearden-CT (n.d.) [re: research materials] Contacts list, lists of questions, news clippings, press releases, transcript of interview of Bearden for Essence magazine Large hand-drawn map of Harlem (area bounded by Lenox and 8th Aves. and 130th and 145th Sts.) showing businesses and individuals' residences 3 photographs of Paris with descriptions on the reverse (possibly by Bearden). (Box 17, Folder II.A.70)
    - Profile: "Putting Something Over Something Else," Romare Bearden, 11/28/1977; Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin (January 1969), two exhibition catalogs of Bearden and two on Horace Pippin and Jacob Lawrence. (Box 17, Folder II.A.71)
    - Profile: "Putting Something Over Something Else," Romare Bearden, 11/28/1977; Exhibition catalogs, news clippings, typescript draft with hand edits ("author's original") (5/27/1975). (Box 18, Folder II.A.72)
    - Profile: "Look What I've Got Here," Claes Oldenburg, 12/12/1977; News clippings, articles, press releases, installation program, ephemera, mostly related to purchase and unveiling of Bat Column, bibliographic and research notes, photocopy of translation of catalogue text for Oldenburg show at the Stedelijk Museum, Amsterdam, sheet of reminiscences by Oldenburg's father. (Box 18, Folder II.A.73)
    - Profile: "Look What I've Got Here," Claes Oldenburg, 12/12/1977; Photocopy of Profile, typescript draft with hand edits (5/9/1977), reader correspondence. (Box 18, Folder II.A.74)
    - Profile: "A Good Monster," Pontus Hulten, 1/16/1978; Two booklets on the Pompidou Center [one with annotations], typescript draft with hand edits (9/6/1977). (Box 18, Folder II.A.75)
    - Profile: "A Good Eye and a Good Ear," Leo Castelli, 5/26/1980; 1 TLS Dr. Bernard Brodsky-TNY (10/26/1975) [re: response to article on Castelli] 1 TLS Constance Trimble-CT (2/12/n.y.) [re: Abstract Expressionists response to Jasper Johns and younger generation of artists] Contact lists, research notes, articles, news clippings, photocopy of New York City cultural award certificate presented to Castelli, unsigned reminiscences of Castelli on Sperone Westwater Fischer letterhead, small sheet of quotes from Sperone, typescript draft of Profile (3/5/1976). (Box 18, Folder II.A.76)
    - Profile: "A Good Eye and a Good Ear," Leo Castelli, 5/26/1980; Research notes, article, tear sheets of Profile. (Box 18, Folder II.A.77)
    - Profile: "The Space Around Real Things," Frank Stella, 9/10/1984; News clippings, articles, tear sheets, press release, research, bibliographic and chronological notes, photocopies of notes by Stella [probably from Norton Lectures] and interview with Stella by Henry Geldzahler, proposal to TNY for Profile on Stella (8/18/1983), exhibition invitations, pamphlets and catalogs, typescript article by unknown author. (Box 18, Folder II.A.78)
    - Profile: "The Space Around Real Things," Frank Stella, 9/10/1984; Tear sheets of Profile, correspondence in response to publication, magazine article, typescript draft with hand edits. (Box 18, Folder II.A.79)
    - Profile: "Getting Everything In," Jennifer Bartlett, 4/15/1985; Interview notes with Bartlett, news clippings, exhibition catalogs, typescript draft, with hand edits, of Bartlett article as composed for catalogue of exhibition at the Walker Art Center and reprinted as a Profile. (Box 18, Folder II.A.80)
    - Profile: "Sharpening the Eye," William S. Rubin, 11/4/1985; Tear sheets of Profile, research and interview notes, contacts lists, news clippings, articles, MoMA brochures, press releases, fact sheets and other materials, most describing effects of 1984 museum expansion. (Box 18, Folder II.A.81)
    - Profile: "Sharpening the Eye," William S. Rubin, 11/4/1985; Photocopies of drafts and final texts of Rubin's and Kirk Varnedoe's replies to negative review of Primitivism in 20th Century Art by Thomas McEvilley in Artforum and draft of later Rubin rebuttal to McEvilley's response, articles, news clippings, MoMA press releases relating to Rubin's career. (Box 19, Folder II.A.82)
    - Profile: "Stage Pictures," Rosamond Bernier, 1/19/1987; 1 ALS "John"-CT (6/20/1985) [re: Jennifer Bartlett, Richard Schulman and Bernier] Tear sheets of Profile, catalogue of the exhibition Miró/Artigas: Terres de Grand Feu, at the Pierre Matisse Gallery, with essay by Bernier, contacts list. (Box 19, Folder II.A.83)
    - Profile: "Colored Muds in a Sticky Substance," John M. Brealey, 3/16/1987; Tear sheets of Profile, material on Alexander Eliot and the restoration of the Sistine Chapel, lecture, "Who Needs a Conservator," by Brealey (10/1/1983), news clippings, articles, photocopied character testaments regarding Brealy's possible move to the Metropolitan Museum, research notes. (Box 19, Folder II.A.84)
    - Profile: "Colored Muds in a Sticky Substance," John M. Brealey, 3/16/1987; Press releases, news clippings, research notes (outline of Profile or binder index,) materials related to the International Centre for the Study of the Preservation and Conservation of Cultural Properties (ICCROM), contacts list. (Box 19, Folder II.A.85)
    - A Reporter at Large: "Irises," Art Auctions, 4/4/1988; Typescript draft of unpublished Profile on David Nash (8/7/1987), news clippings, research notes. (Box 19, Folder II.A.86)
    - A Reporter at Large: "Irises," Art Auctions, 4/4/1988; [Original folder title: "Tanguy et al. (Doucet, Mirbeau, Fnon, Poiet)"] Copies of articles and book extracts. (Box 19, Folder II.A.87)
    - A Reporter at Large: "Irises," Art Auctions, 4/4/1988; [Original folder title: "Notes and Misc."] 1 TLS Gary Tinterow-CT (12/5/1987) [re: Tanguy and van Gogh collecting] Contact lists, research notes and interview summaries, pamphlets and auction listings, news clippings, after sales reports from Sotheby's, documents relating B. Gerald Cantor's history of collecting and philanthropic activities. (Box 19, Folder II.A.88)
    - A Reporter at Large: "Irises," Art Auctions, 4/4/1988; [Original folder title: "Sotheby's-Irises II"] News clippings, articles, research notes, tear sheets of article. (Box 19, Folder II.A.89)
    - A Reporter at Large: "Irises," Art Auctions, 4/4/1988; [Original folder title: "Irises and Paysons and Maine"] News clippings, articles, press releases for the sale of the painting, curriculum vitae of John Whitney Payson, official photographs of Payson and Irises, catalogue of the Joan Whitney Payson Gallery of Art. (Box 19, Folder II.A.90)
    - A Reporter at Large: "Irises," Art Auctions, 4/4/1988; [Original folder title: "Prices at Auction"] News clippings, articles and pamphlets on auction prices. (Box 19, Folder II.A.91)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "Hear," Max Neuhaus, 10/24/1988; Tear sheets of article, pamphlets, exhibition ephemera, articles, Neuhaus curriculum vitae, artist statements, contact and research notes, transcripts of interviews between Neuhaus and other individuals. (Box 20, Folder II.A.92)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "Hear," Max Neuhaus, 10/24/1988; Articles, news clippings, artist statements, pamphlets, typescript draft of article with hand edits (n.d). (Box 20, Folder II.A.93)
    - Profile: "A Sense of Urgency," Marian Wright Edelman, 3/27/1989; Edelman family photograph, tear sheets of Profile, news clippings, articles, press releases, research notes, expenses. (Box 20, Folder II.A.94)
    - Profile: "Open, Available, Useful," Siah Armajani, 3/19/1990; Photocopy of Profile, press releases, news clippings, postcards, articles, five slides of Armajani works, contact lists, materials on related artists such as Isamu Noguchi, Scott Burton and James Turrell, photocopies of TNY Art World articles by CT on public and outdoor art. (Box 20, Folder II.A.95)
    - Profile: "Open, Available, Useful," Siah Armajani, 3/19/1990; 1 ALS Siah Armajani-CT (n.d.) Research and interview notes, news clippings, articles, including materials on Tilted Arc by Richard Serra, photocopy of typescript Profile draft (n.d). (Box 20, Folder II.A.96)
    - Profile: "For the Nation," J. Carter Brown, 9/3/1990; [Original folder title: "Natl. Gallery-History of"] Press releases, news clippings, articles, book chapters, research notes on Andrew Mellon, the history of the National Gallery and specific artworks in the museum. (Box 20, Folder II.A.97)
    - Profile: "For the Nation," J. Carter Brown, 9/3/1990; Photocopy of Profile, news clippings, articles, chronology of major events at the museum. (Box 20, Folder II.A.98)
    - Profile: "For the Nation," J. Carter Brown, 9/3/1990; News clippings, articles on art collectors, museum brochure, press releases, correspondence with museum, contact lists, transcript of National Press Club speech by Brown. (Box 20, Folder II.A.99)
    - Profile: "A Single Person Making a Single Thing," Richard Benson, 12/17/1990; 1 TLS Lincoln Kirstein-CT (9/23/1990) Bulletin of the Newport Historical Society, news clippings, gallery brochures, press releases, research notes. (Box 21, Folder II.A.100)
    - Profile: "A Single Person Making a Single Thing," Richard Benson, 12/17/1990; Tear sheets of Profile, typescript draft with hand annotations (9/10/1990), reader correspondence. (Box 21, Folder II.A.101)
    - Profile: "A Touch for the Now," Walter Hopps, 7/29/1991; Photocopy of Profile, research and interview notes, 1 3.5" computer floppy disk, labeled "Walter Hopps Profile text, Calvin Tomkins 3/18/1991," contents of disk include draft Profile (3/18/1991) and two separate title pages labeled "revised" (2/21, 3/15/1991), all documents printed out. (Box 21, Folder II.A.102)
    - Profile: "A Touch for the Now," Walter Hopps, 7/29/1991; 1 TLS Eleanor Dickinson-TNY (11/26/n.y.) [re: correcting fact in Profile] Contacts list, news clippings, articles, photocopy of large portion of The Last Time I Saw Farus, a history of the Farus Gallery, expenses, research and interview notes. (Box 21, Folder II.A.103)
    - Profile: "A Touch for the Now," Walter Hopps, 7/29/1991; Typescript draft of Profile (3/18/1991). (Box 21, Folder II.A.104)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Piano Principle," Renzo Piano, 8/22/1994; 1 TLS CT-Tina [i.e. Tina Brown] (3/21/1994) [re: possible publication dates for Piano article] Photocopy of article, 1 3.5" computer floppy disk, labeled "Profile: Renzo Piano by Calvin Tomkins," contents of disk includes draft (n.d., but document last modifed 5/25/1993) document printed out, research notes, contact information, correspondence, articles, news clippings, typescript draft of article. (Box 21, Folder II.A.105)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Piano Principle," Renzo Piano, 8/22/1994; 2 TLS CT-Renzo Piano (9/12/1992, 2/22/1993) [re: proposing article and arranging interviews] News clipppings, articles, exhibition pamphlet, research correspondence, contact information, notes. (Box 21, Folder II.A.106)
    - Profile: "The World of Carmel Snow," Carmel Snow, 12/7/1994; Tear sheets of Profile, news clippings, articles, press release, 1 3.5" computer floppy disk, labeled "Carmel Snow (Calvin Tomkins)(WordPerfect 5.1)," contents of disk includes draft Profile (n.d.), document printed out. (Box 21, Folder II.A.107)
    - Profile: "The World of Carmel Snow," Carmel Snow, 12/7/1994; Interview notes and transcripts, many interviews conducted by DK, many notes possibly in her hand. (Box 21, Folder II.A.108)
    - Profile: "The World of Carmel Snow," Carmel Snow, 12/7/1994; Interview notes and transcripts, photocopies of book excerpts, entire legal notepad of chronology and other notes, many interviews conducted by DK, many notes possibly in her hand. (Box 22, Folder II.A.109)
    - Profile: "Artist Unknown," Albert York, 6/19/1995; Tear sheets of Profile, articles, gallery pamphlets and announcements, 1 3.5" computer floppy disk, labeled "Albert York Profile (Tomkins)(WordPerfect 5.1)," contents of disk includes draft Profile (n.d.), document printed out, interview notes and transcripts, press releases. (Box 22, Folder II.A.110)
    - Profile: "Artist Unknown," Albert York, 6/19/1995; Interview notes and transcripts, press releases, news clippings, photocopy of draft typescript with hand annotations (4/24/1995), earlier undated typescript of Profile, blank note cards of York's artwork. (Box 22, Folder II.A.111)
    - Profile: "Artist Unknown," Albert York, 6/19/1995; 1 TLS Tina Brown-CT (4/5/1995) [re: suggested edits to Profile] Expenses, correspondence from Virginia York concerning interviews, blank note cards of York's artwork, gallery catalogue of group show, two spiral notepads detailing specific York works, size, date and material, purchase date, sale price and purchaser, notepads found in following folder on Dan Kiley. (Box 22, Folder II.A.112)
    - Profile: "The Garden Artist," Dan Kiley, 10/16/1995; 1 TL facsimile Tina Brown-CT (9/25/1995) [re: edits to Profile] Photocopy of Profile, typescript draft with hand annotations, memos relating to fact checking of Profile, reproductions of Kiley works and sketches. (Box 22, Folder II.A.113)
    - Profile: "The Garden Artist," Dan Kiley, 10/16/1995; Twenty-one 3x5 color photographs of Kiley-designed landscape, some images with Kiley, many labeled "Kiley/Salisbury," news clippings, articles, photocopies of book passages, contact lists, issue of Inland Architect, photocopy of site inspection and initial design suggestions, from the office of Dan Kiley to Edgar and Clarissa Bronfman (8/14/1995), regarding their property Hammersley Hill. (Box 22, Folder II.A.114)
    - Profile: "The Garden Artist," Dan Kiley, 10/16/1995; 1 ALS Dan Kiley-CT and DK (7/22/1995) [re: recent interview, more meetings for Profile and progress on the Bronfman estate] Articles, news clippings, photocopy of report on progress of research and documentation for biography of Kiley by Jane Amidon (7/1995), contacts lists, bibliographical notes. (Box 22, Folder II.A.115)
    - Profile: "The Garden Artist," Dan Kiley, 10/16/1995; Articles, news clippings and spiral-bound company curriculum vitae of Martha Schwartz, Inc. landscape architects. (Box 22, Folder II.A.116)
    - Profile: "The Garden Artist," Dan Kiley, 10/16/1995; Process: Architecture 108 (February 1983), Japanese periodical, issue title: "Dan Kiley: Landscape Design II," curriculum vitae of the Office of Dan Kiley. (Box 22, Folder II.A.117)
    - The Sky Line: "The Maverick," Frank Gehry, 7/7/1997; Tear sheets of article, articles, news clippings. (Box 23, Folder II.A.118)
    - The Sky Line: "The Maverick," Frank Gehry, 7/7/1997; 1 TLS CT-Frank Gehry (9/30/1996) [re: proposal for Profile] 1 facsimile TLS Frank Gehry-CT (3/27/1997) 1 TLS CT-Claes Oldenburg (4/9/1997) [re: experiences with Gehry] Contact lists, research notes and correspondence, articles, news clippings, book excerpts, pamphlets, biographical materials from Frank O. Gehry & Associates. (Box 23, Folder II.A.119)
    - The Sky Line: "The Maverick," Frank Gehry, 7/7/1997; [Original folder title: "Most recent"] Facsimile correspondence from Frank O. Gehry & Associates regarding client Eli Broad and final fact checking of article, interview summary with Broad and Gehry, research notes and correspondence regarding Disney Hall. (Box 23, Folder II.A.120)
    - The Sky Line: "The Maverick," Frank Gehry, 7/7/1997; [Original folder title: "Disney Hall"] Booklet of Disney Hall design from Frank O. Gehry & Associates (5/1/1998), news clippings, press releases, research notes. (Box 23, Folder II.A.121)
    - The Sky Line: "The Maverick," Frank Gehry, 7/7/1997; [Original folder title: "Gehry-Bilbao"] Pamphlet of the museum, press release, map of Bilbao, news clippings, articles, research correspondence. (Box 23, Folder II.A.122)
    - The Sky Line: "The Maverick," Frank Gehry, 7/7/1997; [Original folder title: "Other architects"] News clippings, articles, press releases. (Box 23, Folder II.A.123)
    - The Sky Line: "The Maverick," Frank Gehry, 7/7/1997; Three typescript drafts of article (5/26/1997 with hand edits, n.d., 4/28/1997). (Box 23, Folder II.A.124)
    - Profile: "The Importance of Being Elitist," Philippe de Montebello, 11/24/1997; 1 TLS Arthur Rosenblatt-Tina Brown (11/24/1997) [re: corrections to Profile, includes memo detailing de Montebello's rebuttal] Photocopy of Profile, news clippings, articles, five typescript drafts of Profile, each with various hand edits (10/20/1997, and the rest undated). (Box 23, Folder II.A.125)
    - Profile: "The Importance of Being Elitist," Philippe de Montebello, 11/24/1997; News clippings, brochures, articles, press releases, research and biographical notes, interview correspondence, interview glosses and summaries, contact lists. (Box 23, Folder II.A.126)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Benefactor," Dominique de Menil, 6/8/1998; Newspaper and magazine articles, press releases relating to de Menil and the Menil Collection. (Box 23, Folder II.A.127)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Benefactor," Dominique de Menil, 6/8/1998; [Original folder title: "Remarks made by others about Dominique de Menil"] Photocopies of historical and contemporary reflections on de Menil, two pamphlets from the Carter-Menil Human Rights Prize Awards. (Box 24, Folder II.A.128)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Benefactor," Dominique de Menil, 6/8/1998; Tear sheets of article, typescript draft of article (n.d). (Box 24, Folder II.A.129)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Benefactor," Dominique de Menil, 6/8/1998; News clippings, articles, press releases, fact checking correspondence to Susan Sontag and others, programs from de Menil's memorial services, research notes, index to research binder, contact list. (Box 24, Folder II.A.130)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Benefactor," Dominique de Menil, 6/8/1998; 1 ACS Sylvie Boissonnas (sister to de Menil)-CT (2/28/1998) 1 ALS Jim Love-CT (n.d.) [re: personal recollections of de Menil] News clippings, articles, interview appointment schedule and contact list, research notes and correspondence, photograph and transparency of portraits of de Menil by Max Ernst and Andy Warhol. (Box 24, Folder II.A.131)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Benefactor," Dominique de Menil, 6/8/1998; [Original folder titles: "catalogue introductions by Dominique de Menil" and "Quotations enjoyed by Dominique de Menil"] Photocopies of her writings and favorite passages. (Box 24, Folder II.A.132)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Man Who Walks on Air," Philippe Petit, 4/5/1999; Tear sheets of article, typescript draft of article with hand edits (n.d.), research notes, official pamphlets and material on Petit's projects Canyon Walk and Tour et Fil, news clippings. (Box 24, Folder II.A.133)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Man Who Walks on Air," Philippe Petit, 4/5/1999; 2 facsimile ALS Philippe Petit-CT (9/16, 10/6/1998) Two bound transcripts of talks and film of Petit, articles and news clippings, research notes. (Box 24, Folder II.A.134)
    - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "The Man Who Walks on Air," Philippe Petit, 4/5/1999; Guide book to the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, New York, guide book to the Grand Canyon. (Box 24, Folder II.A.135)
    - Profile: "After Shock," Damien Hirst, 9/20/1999; Photocopy of Profile, typescript draft of Profile with hand edits (n.d.), contact lists, research correspondence, notes biographical materials, news clippings, articles. (Box 24, Folder II.A.136)
    - Profile: "After Shock," Damien Hirst, 9/20/1999; News clippings, articles, some small notes and research correspondence, exhibition booklet and ephemera. (Box 24, Folder II.A.137)
    - Profile: "An Eye for the New," Ileana Sonnabend, 1/17/2000; Photocopy of Profile, news clippings, articles, gallery ephemera, interview summary and transcript, notes, correspondence. (Box 25, Folder II.A.138)
    - Profile: "An Eye for the New," Ileana Sonnabend, 1/17/2000; Research binder index, partial typescript draft of Profile (n.d.), research and interview notes.; Additional typescript draft of Profile is located in folder III.129, Postscript: "The Lion," 9/6/1999. (Box 25, Folder II.A.139)
    - Profile: "Her Secret Identities," Cindy Sherman, 5/15/2000; Photocopy of Profile, typescript draft of Profile with hand edits and cover letter from editor (4/4/n.y.), typescript draft of Profile (3/30/2000), research and interview notes. (Box 25, Folder II.A.140)
    - Profile: "Her Secret Identities," Cindy Sherman, 5/15/2000; News clippings, articles, press releases. (Box 25, Folder II.A.141)
    - Profile: "The Tennis Artist," John McEnroe, 9/4/2000; 1 facsimile TLS David Remnick-CT (7/17/2000) Photocopy of Profile, typescript draft of Profile with hand edits (7/28/2000), news clippings, articles, book extracts, official transcripts of interviews with McEnroe, contact list. (Box 25, Folder II.A.142)
    - Profile: "The Big Picture," Andreas Gursky, 1/22/2001; Photocopy of Profile, tear sheet of Profile reprint in Modern Painters, curriculum vitae of Gursky, research notes, correspondence, interview transcripts from other sources, expense receipts, news clippings, articles. (Box 25, Folder II.A.143)
    - Profile: "Schnabel in Lights," Julian Schnabel, 3/19/2001; 1 ALS CT and DK-Damien Hirst (2/15/2001) [re: Schnabel] Photocopy of Profile, typescript draft of Profile (n.d.), news clippings, articles, research and bibliographical notes, interview extracts, correspondence. (Box 25, Folder II.A.144)
    - Profile: "The Modernist," Kirk Varnedoe, 11/5/2001; Tear sheets of Profile, typescript draft with hand edits (n.d.), press releases, news clippings, articles, brochures, lecture notes from Varnedoe, copies of emails concerning his cancer, research notes, typescript draft review of Modern Starts: Things[MoMA Exh. #1838, November 17(21), 1999-March 14, 2000] by Frank Stella. (Box 25, Folder II.A.145)
    - Profile: "The Modernist," Kirk Varnedoe, 11/5/2001; News clippings, articles, research correspondence, interview quotes and summary of William Rubin (2/16/1973). (Box 25, Folder II.A.146)